A Finding Aid to the Paul Ryan papers, 1931-2009, in the Archives of American Art AAA.ryanpaul
Archives of American Art
- Project Files, 1968-2008; Series 5; 6.5 Linear feet Boxes 11-17, 20, OV 21-22, 24, RD 26
  - Environmental Projects, 5.1
    - New York City Eco-Channel for a Sustainable Tomorrow (NEST) (Box 12)
      - Correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - Notes, circa 1990 (Box 12, Folder 11)
      - Petition, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - Printed Material, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 13)
        Oversized material in OV 21.
      - Testimony at Hearing on Cable Access, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 14)
      - Writings and Circulars, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 15-17)
    - Talking Wood (Box 12)
      - Photographs from Watershed Watch, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 18)
      - Notes, circa 1978-1979 (Box 12, Folder 19-20)
    - Tapping on Water, 1997-1999 (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Unidentified Earthscore Projects (Box 13)
      - Lake Minnewaska Video Shotlist, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Notes on Unidentified Waterfall, circa 1990 (Box 13, Folder 2)
        Oversized item in OV 24.
      - Photographs, circa 1988 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Proposals (Box 13)
      - The Adirondacks, Ecology Music Video, circa 1987 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Art, Computers, and Environment, circa 1988 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Beaching and Birthing in Jamaica Bay, 1987 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Delaware Water Gap, circa 1980 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Channel W - Your Wire to the Watershed, circa 1980 (Box 13, Folder 8-10)
      - Coast of Cape Ann: Score for a Videoscape, 1984; 1980 (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Communications for the Riverside Park Community, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 12)
      - Eco-Channel Design, circa 1983-1987 (Box 13, Folder 13-16)
      - Experiment in Community Cable Origination, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 17)
      - Mountain Waters, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 18)
      - NYC/Ecology: A Proposal for a Thirteen-Part Television Series, circa 1990 (Box 13, Folder 19)
      - New York City Forests, circa 1988 (Box 13, Folder 20)
      - Pine Barrens Video, circa 1990 (Box 13, Folder 21)
      - The Role of the Cathedral in the Ecological Age, 1984-1985 (Box 13, Folder 22)
      - The Shawangunk Symphony, circa 1990 (Box 13, Folder 23)
      - Symphony for the Jersey Shore, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 24)
      - Video Interpretation of the Devil's Kitchen, circa 1997 (Box 13, Folder 25)
      - Video Proposal for Bioregional Conference, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 26)
      - Watershed Watch, circa 1981 (Box 13, Folder 27)
      - Proposals by Others, circa 1980-1993 (Box 13, Folder 28)
    - Oversized NEST Printed Material from box 12, folder 13. (Box OV 21)
    - Oversized Notes on Unidentified Waterfall from box 13, folder 2 (Box OV 24)
  - Threeing Projects, 5.2
    Ryan's work on the use of video to create a self-correcting system of relationships through scored routines of interactions are referred to throughout the collection as "triadic behavior," "relational practice," or "threeing." This series includes documentation from projects related to threeing such as the Triadic Tapes (aka "Inventing Triadic Behavior"), the Circuit, which is courseware for implementing threeing concepts into education, the Consensus computer program, the ICM method, the Behavior Invention Marathon, the Tricultural Tournament, the Hall of Risk, exhibited at the 2002 Venice Biennale, and many others.
    Also found are records related to threeing in general and not a specific project, such as notes and flyers for workshops or demonstrations. Kleinform illustrations include sketches, finished drawings, and Photostats of a visual element of threeing exercises. Several of these illustrations were created by Claude Ponsot and published in Ryan's writings about Triadic behavior. The threeing rug design project was in part a collaboration with the artist Michael Kalil. Sketches and diagrams documenting the project contain a variety of media, from quick pencil sketches to color prints.
    Also found are 35 videocassettes (U-matic) referred to throughout Ryan's papers as the Triadic Tapes, aka Inventing Triadic Behavior, which document extensive early threeing experiments with dancers at the Ashokan Field Campus of the State University of New York at New Paltz. An additional video recording is found with records for the "Video Variations on Holy Week" workshop on triadic behavior at the Kitchen. Records from the Empowerment Center Retreat include still photographs of Ryan's threeing ritual.
    - The Circuit (Computer Lab and Courseware), 1984; Includes a 5.25 inch floppy disk. (Box 13, Folder 29-30)
    - Consensus (Hypercard Program), 1989-1991 (Box 13, Folder 31)
    - Empowerment Center Retreat Photographs, 2008 (Box 13, Folder 32)
    - Flyers, circa 1985 (Box 13, Folder 33)
    - Hall of Risk Exhibition Prints, 2002 (Box 13, Folder 34)
      Oversized documents stored in rolled document 26.
    - Kleinform Illustrations, 1973-1991 (Box 13, Folder 35)
      Oversized illustrations in Box 20 and OV 21.
    - Notes, circa 1975-1985 (Box 13, Folder 36)
      Oversized notes in OV 22.
    - Rug Design Sketches and Diagrams, circa 1988 (Box 13, Folder 37-38)
      Oversized material in OV 24.
    - Inventing Triadic Behavior (Box 13)
      See box 17, folder 9 for list of video tapes from this and other projects.
      - Notes and Writings, circa 1976-1986 (Box 13, Folder 39)
      - Poster Design, circa 1976 (Box 13, Folder 40)
        Oversized items in OV 22.
      - Video, Ashokan Field Campus, 1975; 4 Videocassettes (U-matic) Tapes labeled 116, 117, 118, 119 30 minute tapes (Box 13, Folder 41-42)
      - Video, Ashokan Field Campus, 1975; 14 Videocassettes (U-matic) Tapes numbered 120-127 and 133-138 30 minute tapes (Box 14, Folder 1-7)
      - Video, Ashokan Field Campus, 1975; 6 Videocassettes (U-matic) Tapes numbered 139-141, 211, 220-221 30 minute tapes (Box 15, Folder 1-3)
      - Video, Dance Studio, circa 1976; 8 Videocassettes (U-matic) Tapes numbered 159, 169, 209, 210, 212-215 30 minute tapes (Box 15, Folder 4-7)
      - Video, Dance Studio, circa 1976; 2 Videocassettes (U-matic) Tapes numbered 216 and 217 30 minute tapes (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Video, Backhoe and Dumptruck, circa 1976; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Tape numbered 218 30 minute tape (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Video Variations on Holy Week (Box 16)
      - Notes and Photographs, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - Poster, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 4)
        Oversized posters in OV 22.
      - Workshop Video, 1976; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Tape numbered 219 30 minute tape (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Proposals (Box 16)
      - The Electronic Classroom, 1987; 1984 (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - An Explanation of Violence in Families, circa 1982 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - House of Threes, 2003 (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - How to Three, 1999 (Box 16, Folder 9)
      - Infomorph Two: Information Stock Exchange, circa 1980 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Intercultural Behavior Composition #1, circa 1985 (Box 16, Folder 11)
        Other drafts included have the titles "Threeing" and "Triadic Tournament"
      - Jazz Video Wall, circa 2000 (Box 16, Folder 12)
      - Melusina, 1981 (Box 16, Folder 13)
      - Multicultural Threeing, 1999 (Box 16, Folder 14)
      - Practice without Instruments, circa 1980 (Box 16, Folder 15)
      - Relational Practice, 1987 (Box 16, Folder 16)
      - Ritual of Triadic Relationships, circa 1984-1985 (Box 16, Folder 17)
      - A Sustaining Practice for Organizers, circa 1995 (Box 16, Folder 18)
      - Three of You (Video Game), circa 1980 (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - A Triad of Women, 1981 (Box 16, Folder 20)
      - Tricultural Tournament, 1990 (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - Oversized Kleinform Illustrations from Box 13, folder 35. (Box 20)
    - Oversized Kleinform Illustrations from box 13, folder 35 (Box OV 21)
    - Oversized Notes on Threeing Projects from box 13, folder 36 (Box OV 22)
    - Oversized Poster Design for Inventing Triadic Behavior from box 13, folder 40 (Box OV 22)
    - Oversized Poster for Video Variations on Holy Week from box 16, folder 4 (Box OV 22)
    - Oversized Rug Design Sketches and Diagrams from box 13, folders 37-38 (Box OV 24)
    - Oversized Hall of Risk Exhibition Prints from box 13, folder 34 (Box RD 26)
  - Other Projects, 5.3
    Other projects include performances, freelance jobs, and art projects. Contracts and agreements include a loan agreement with Ira Schneider of Raindance for video equipment borrowed from Ryan in 1969. Ryan's research on video uses and equipment include correspondence, notes, and brochures for video equipment.
    Tethys was an environmental artwork by Bob Schuler involving a round-the-world sea voyage on which Ryan traveled. His project documenting the journey is referred to in his records as "What the Camera Conceals." Tethys files include photographs of Ryan, Schuler, and crew, as well as proposals and notes on Ryan's video production. "Video Wake for My Father" was a project that spanned nearly twenty years, beginning as a taped private performance, then becoming a video and public performance, and later a published play accompanied by poetry by Ryan's brother, Jim Ryan. One sound cassette of Ryan reading the piece is also found.
    Among the proposals in this series is a long essay reflecting on Ryan's stint as the first reviewer of grant proposals to the New York State Council on the Arts in the field of video during the 1970s. Another proposal concerns the preservation of his video recordings, which includes a printed report from a database of hundreds of tapes shot by Ryan, including all the tapes in this collection.
    See 1986 Notebooks in series 3, Writings, more notes relating to Tethys.
    - Contracts and Agreements, 1969-1994 (Box 16, Folder 22)
      Includes a loan agreement for video equipment with Ira Schneider from 1969.
    - Dinosaur: The Fourth World, 1987-1989 (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - Research on Video Uses and Equipment, 1968-1969 (Box 16, Folder 24)
      Oversized notes in Box 20.
    - Tethys, or "What the Camera Conceals" (Box 16)
      - Catalog and Exhibition Announcement, 1986 (Box 16, Folder 25)
      - Photographs, 1986 (Box 16, Folder 26)
        Oversized photographs in Box 20.
      - Proposals, 1986-1988 (Box 16, Folder 27)
      - Video Editing Notes, circa 1986 (Box 16, Folder 28)
    - Video Compositions: "Video Composition for One," and "Hands-Face", circa 1970 (Box 16, Folder 29)
    - Video Wake for My Father (Box 16)
      - Invitation to Original Performance, 1971 (Box 16, Folder 30)
      - Transcripts and Edits, circa 1971 (Box 16, Folder 31-36)
    - Video Wake for My Father (Box 17)
      - Edited Versions, 1988; 1973 (Box 17, Folder 1-3)
        Includes loose and bound manuscripts of 1973 version, and a manuscript of 1988 version.
      - Video Wake Reconstructions, 1987; Includes one sound cassette. (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - As Published in Fire, Water, Fathe r, 1996 (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - Submission to POV (Television Program), 1990 (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - Letter Regarding Copyright, 1992 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Proposals (Box 17)
      - Proposal Regarding the Video Peer Review Process at the New York State Council on the Arts, 1987 (Box 17, Folder 8)
      - Video Preservation, 2000; 1991 (Box 17, Folder 9)
        Contains a database printout entitled "Paul Ryan Tape Database: Tape List."
      - "Water Fire Water" and "Water Children", 1995 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Oversized Notes from Research on Video Uses and Equipment from box 16, folder 24 (Box 20)
    - Oversized Photographs of Tethys Crew from box 16, folder 26 (Box 20)
- Teaching Files, 1967-2008; Series 6; 0.7 Linear feet Box 17
  Series contains contracts, syllabi, course descriptions, teacher evaluations, workshop descriptions, notes in development of courses, grant proposal for course development, student work, correspondence related to academic job hunting. Records in this series relate to teaching jobs Ryan held at The Hudson School, the Dalton School, Ramapo College, and Savannah college of Art and Design, as well as teaching projects and workshops supported by various organizations and government agencies. Course subjects include media, communications, video production, environment, theory, semiotics, and the Earthscore system applied in various educational contexts. Multiple curricula are found combining video production training with environmental education, particularly the Black Rock Rangers at Dalton School, and the Urban Conservation Corps Video Pilot Program.
  Additional material related to Ryan's teaching is found in Biographical Material and Correspondence.
  - Course Descriptions, circa 1975-2000 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Job Search, 1968; 1989-1997 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Student Work, circa 1980 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Dalton School (Box 17)
    - Black Rock Rangers, 1988-1992 (Box 17, Folder 15-19)
    - Education Empowerment Workshop, 1997 (Box 17, Folder 20-22)
    - Laboratory for Applied Pedagogy, 1989 (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - Virtual Environmental Studies Program, 1997 (Box 17, Folder 24)
  - Workshops, circa 1969-2000 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Hudson School (Box 17)
    - Correspondence, Contracts, and Printed Material, 1983-1984 (Box 17, Folder 25)
    - Grade Books, circa 1983-1985 (Box 17, Folder 26-28)
  - ICM Method Videoscript, 1988 (Box 17, Folder 28)
  - Merchant Marine School, 1967 (Box 17, Folder 29)
  - Newburgh Media Project, 1969-1970 (Box 17, Folder 30)
  - The New School for Social Research, 1997-2008; 1984 (Box 17, Folder 31)
  - Outline for Communications Workshop, circa 1980 (Box 17, Folder 32)
  - Savannah College of Art and Design, 1992-1994 (Box 17, Folder 33-34)
  - Sheboygan County Education Association, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 35)
  - Success Skills Program, 1995 (Box 17, Folder 36)
  - Urban Conservaiton Corps Pilot Video Program, 1990-1991 (Box 17, Folder 37-38)
- Printed Material, 1968-2009; Series 7; 1.6 Linear feet Boxes 18-20, OV 23, 25
  Series contains books, newspaper clippings, conference programs and published proceedings, exhibition catalogs and announcements, film and video programs, flyers, periodicals, poetry publications, and posters, and materials relating to the artist Al Robbins, which includes an obituary written by Ryan. Also found are publications of the Raindance Corporation, which have been filed together under that heading. Raindance publications include the book, Guerrilla Television (1971), and four issues of their magazine, Radical Software (1971-1972). Most of the material in this series was either written by Paul Ryan, contains articles by Paul Ryan, or documents activities of Paul Ryan. Other materials found contain works by Ryan's associates and collaborators.
  Arrangement is alphabetical by type, then chronologically within each type. Additional material related to the Raindance Corporation is found in series 4, Organizational Records. Additional writings in draft form are in series 3, Writings. Illustrations from many of Ryan's publications found here are found in draft and mechanical form in series 5.2, Threeing Projects. Additional posters related to projects are found in series 5, Project Files.
  - Books (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Art As Inquiry by Marga Bijovoet, 1994 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Birth and Death and Cybernation, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Cybernetics of the Sacred, 1974 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Doubleaught, 2000 (Box 18, Folder 4)
      Contains the article "Development of the Relational Circuit" by Paul Ryan
    - TVTV Primetime Prospectus, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Clippings (Box 18)
    - Articles by and Interviews with Paul Ryan, 1981-1991 (Box 18, Folder 6)
      See also Reprints. Oversized clippings in OV 23.
    - Articles about Ryan, 1979-1996 (Box 18, Folder 7)
      Oversized clippings in OV 23.
    - General, circa 1983-1998 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Conference Programs and Proceedings (Box 18)
    - Matrix, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - A Celebration of the Hudson Valley Environment, 1983 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - The Media Arts in Transition, 1983 (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Is the Earth a Living Organism? Conference Produced by National Audobon Society Expedition Institute, 1985-1986 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Creativity: The Semiotic Society of America, 1997 (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - General File, circa 1978-2009 (Box 18, Folder 14-15)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements (Box 18)
    - Nam June Paik: electronic art II, 1968; Inscribed by Paik (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - TV as a Creative Medium, 1969 (Box 18, Folder 17)
    - Vision and Television, 1970 (Box 18, Folder 18)
    - Video Art, 1975 (Box 18, Folder 19)
    - Al Robbins: Anticatastrophe, 1980 (Box 18, Folder 20)
    - Abstract Painting: 1960-1969, 1983 (Box 18, Folder 21)
    - Avenues of Thought, 1987 (Box 18, Folder 22)
    - Surveillance, 1987 (Box 18, Folder 23)
      Oversized material in box 20.
    - Set In Motion, 1994 (Box 18, Folder 24)
    - Lightshowers, 2007 (Box 18, Folder 25)
    - Other Exhibitions, 1976-2005 (Box 18, Folder 26)
  - Film and Video Festival Programs, 1982-2004 (Box 18, Folder 27)
  - Flyers for Lectures, Screenings and Performances, circa 1969-2004 (Box 18, Folder 28)
  - Other Flyers and Pamphlets, 1976-1997 (Box 18, Folder 29)
  - Periodicals (Box 18)
    - Educators Guide to Media and Methods, 1968 December (Box 18, Folder 30)
    - Media and Methods, Exploration in Education, 1969 October (Box 18, Folder 31)
    - Audiovisual Instruction, 1969 November (Box 18, Folder 32)
    - Talking Wood and Watershed Watch, 1979 (Box 18, Folder 33)
    - Cybernetic Magazine Prospectus, 1982 (Box 18, Folder 34)
    - TeleVisions, 1976 Summer (Box 18, Folder 35)
      Oversized periodical housed in box 20.
    - ArtForum, 1980 September (Box 18, Folder 36)
    - Video 81, 1981 (Box 18, Folder 37)
      Oversized periodical in box 20.
    - AfterImage, 1984-1999 (Box 18, Folder 38)
      Oversized periodicals moved to box 20.
    - Continuing the Conversation: a Newsletter on the Ideas of Gregory Bateson, 1986-1991 (Box 18, Folder 39)
    - IS Journal #5, 1987 (Box 18, Folder 40)
    - Millenium Film Journal No. 22, 1989-1990 (Box 18, Folder 41)
    - Media Matters: A Newsletter of the Media Alliance, 1990-1992 (Box 18, Folder 42)
    - Raise the Stakes: Planet Drum Review, 1993 (Box 18, Folder 43)
      Oversized item moved to box 20.
    - FYI: Mental Health Issues for Artists, 1998 Spring (Box 18, Folder 44)
      Oversized periodical moved to box 20.
    - The New School Observer, 1998 April (Box 18, Folder 45)
    - bob: Interntational Magazine of Space Design (024), 2006 (Box 18, Folder 46)
    - Reprints from Periodicals, 1968-2002 (Box 18, Folder 47)
      Contains reprints of published articles by Paul Ryan, Victor Gioscia, Myrdene Anderson, Morris Berman, and Nelson Goodman.
  - Periodicals (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous Environmental and Political Periodicals, 1968-1991 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous Media Periodicals, 1970-1997 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Poetry, circa 2000 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Posters, circa 1973-1984 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    Oversized posters in OV 25.
  - Raindance Publications (Box 19)
    - Guerrilla Television, 1971 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Radical Software, 1971-1972 (Box 19, Folder 6)
      Oversized editions in box 20 and OV 25.
  - Al Robbins, Memorial Program and Other Materials, 1982-1990 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Oversized Radical Software Issue from Box 19, folder 6 (Box 20)
  - Oversized Clippings from Box 18, folders 6-8 (Box OV 23)
  - Oversized Posters from Box 19, folder 4 (Box OV 25)
  - Oversized Radical Software Issue from Box 19, folder 6 (Box OV 25)
- Artwork, 1965-2003; Series 8; 0.1 Linear feet Boxes 19-20, OV 22
  Series contains artists' books, doodles, illustrations, prints, and photographs by named and unnamed artists. None of the artwork in this series appears to be by Ryan. Notable is an artist's book entitled "Patterns" by Lida Zerella, which incorporates still images from Ryan's Triadic Tapes in a small album. Two illustrations by Claude Ponsot, who also illustrated many of Ryan's publications relating to Kleinform and threeing, are also found.
  Additional artwork is found in series 5.2, Threeing projects. Video used as source material for Linda Zarello's book "Patterns" is also found in series 5.2.
  - Artist's Book "Patterns" by Linda Zarella, Based on Ryan's Triadic Tapes, 1976 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Artist's Book "The Rationales" by Chris Mann, 1986 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Doodles, circa 1965-2002 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Illustrations by Claude Ponsot, circa 1975; 1975 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    Oversized item in OV 22.
  - Photograph by Robert Brooks, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    Oversized item in box 20.
  - Prints and Photographs by Unidentified Artists, 1980-2003 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Oversized Photograph by Robert Brooks from Box 19, folder 12 (Box 20)
  - Oversized Illustration by Claude Ponsot from Box 19, folder 11 (Box OV 22)